Waqas Ahmed, 235- 3025 The Credit Woodlands, Mississauga, ON L5C 2V3 wlahmed@ryerson.ca 647.444.5954

April 3, 2019

30 Forensic Engineering 800 - 40 University Ave Toronto, ON M5J 1T1

Dear Stephanie,

I am writing in response to your Job posting related to Civil/Environmental Engineering. This would be a great opportunity to implement my engineering skills gained through past work experience and academic background towards one of the most reputable forensic engineering firm.

My astonishing experience at Sarafinchin Associates helped me secure invaluable experience of detailed site inspections of soils, concrete side walk / structures and asphalt surfaces as per the building codes as well as performing on site quantity surveying for progress payment certificate. In addition to this I was also actively managing the lab by performing material testing to ensure the compliance of materials as well as performing administrative work related to planning, pricing and closing different projects.

My internship at Halton Region enabled me to research, create various reports and presentations about the region's assets which were presented to the public and senior management. My responsibilities included analyzing site plans for new subdivisions, GIS Data, CCTV, and conducting site visits for detailed inspections of sidewalks, roads, culverts, fences, manhole/sewer repair as well as providing technical support to the engineers in designing the facilities for storm water, potable water and sewage.

At Graham Construction, I was part of a highly complex, multi-year, \$30 million project. The focus of my work involved ensuring quality control as per the contract drawings and specifications, problem-solving using deductive and analytical reasoning, negotiating purchase orders, liaise with the consultants, city departments, and the subcontractor while maintaining a strong team-cohesion by providing administrative support and coordination. The team work at Graham helped in the development of my interpersonal skills to better manage the project team and helped in building on my business acumen.

As a graduate with a bachelor degree in Civil Engineering from Ryerson University my academic capstone project consisted of redesigning the Fifty Rd located in City of Hamilton. Combining the academic and work experience, I believe that being granted an opportunity at 30 forensic would be a great match for my skill set and I would be quite enthusiastic to be included in your upcoming interview schedule for this wonderful opportunity. Please find a copy of my resume attached for your kind review.

Sincerely,

Waqas Ahmed

WAQAS AHMED E.I.T

235 - 3025 The Credit Woodlands Mississauga, ON L5C 2V3

(647)-444-5954

wlahmed@ryerson.ca

QUALIFICATIONS

Dedicated, goal-oriented Engineer in training seeking employment with excellent organization, time management, and decision-making abilities. Technically competent with Strong written, verbal and interpersonal communication skills. Exceptional initiative, work ethic, and the ability to delegate, negotiate and communicate effectively as part of a team.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Proficient in various programs such as AutoCAD Civil, Microsoft, , ArcGIS and Micro Survey.
- Excellent presentation and writing skills with plentiful expertise in preparation of engineering reports.
- Technically proficient with engineering tools such as Sokkia Control Station, SDDR Data Collector, and Nuclear Gauge.
- Invaluable experience of Storm management control, Traffic Engineering and Highway curves using IDF curves, Simtraffic and Traffic Engineering Software (TES) such as HCS, InterCalc, Vissim, and Torus.
- Capable of interpreting data from a variety of sources and resolve problems by selecting the optimal solution.

EDUCATION

Bachelors of Civil Engineering

Ryerson University, Toronto ON. (Sept 2014 – April 2018)

<u>Relevant Coursework</u>: Strengths of Material, Structural Analysis, Transportation Engineering, Highway Design, Asphalt design, Engineering Economics Analysis, Fluid Mechanics and Concrete Design

Civil Engineering Technology (Advanced Diploma)

Humber College, Toronto, ON. (September 2009 – April 2012)

<u>Relevant Coursework:</u> Surveying, Civil CADD, Construction Methods, Material Testing, Construction Management, Estimation, Wastewater and Water Controls, Municipal Services and Traffic Control.

Certified Class 1 Water Operator (December 2011) Member of OACETT and Professional Engineers of Ontario

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Junior Project Engineer/Field Inspector

Sarafinchin Associates, Etobicoke, ON. (May 2018 – Nov 2018)

- Perform daily field inspections of Concrete and Asphalt to assure the compliance with city standards.
- Preparing and testing soil, concrete and Asphalt samples in the lab.
- Ensuring testing is performed in accordance with agreed standards.
- Ensuring consistency in accuracy and timely output of work.
- Administration duties setting up work orders, reports and drawings for senior engineers.
- liaise with contractors, property owners and the general public to address issues and complaints.

WAQAS AHMED E.I.T

235 - 3025 The Credit Woodlands Mississauga, ON L5C 2V3

(647)-444-5954 w1ahmed@ryerson.ca

Water and Waste Water Management Systems Coordinator *Halton Region, Oakville, ON.* (April 2016 – Sept 2016)

- Assisted Systems Planning and Customer Service staff with data acquisition from flow monitoring and rain gauge stations as well as respond to customer inquiries and concerns in a professional way.
- Analyzed and manipulated flow and rain data relationships for casual links to arrive at meaningful outputs.
- Performed Excel spreadsheet manipulation for determining the design requirements of pipes.
- Utilized GIS to enter information into the database and retrieve data for estimates of Capital Budget
- Analyzed engineering drawings and retrieve data as required to perform various job functions.
- Assist the project management of 3 new development projects.
- Inspected Clean water distribution and wastewater collection system using CCTV

Project Coordinator

Graham Construction and Engineering, Mississauga, ON. (April 2012 – April 2013)

- Provided assistance to senior staff (Project Managers/Superintendents) in the coordination, scheduling, quantity surveying, reporting and quality control functions.
- Carried out weekly inspections like Quality Control, Safety, and LEED.
- Produced the LEED reports and handle all the paperwork.
- Created a monthly cost and work progress report for all project components, including excavation, backfill, formwork, rebar, concrete, embedded metals and underground piping.
- Developed and monitored construction schedule with the assistance of the Project Manager and assist PM with the development of bi-weekly schedules.
- Controlled drawings, drawing records, and revisions.
- Reviewed shop drawings and submittals to make sure that they are in accordance with the plan and specifications.
- Control site instructions request for information and change orders.
- Coordinate with the Team to resolve disputes.
- Maintained all QA/QC documentation, maintain records of all testing and inspections. Ensuring that all technical aspects of the work conform to all applicable codes and standards.
- Scheduled meetings and conference calls between the team of Consultants and Contractors.
- Provided written documentation for all clarifications and instructions, attended all regular meetings and note down the minutes.
- Assisted with preparing progress invoicing and progress status reports in SAP.
- Completed estimates, reviewed estimates and assisted in costing and final bidding.

ACADEMIC PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Transportation Capstone: Geometric improvement of Fifty Road in Hamilton (2018)

Analyzed traffic volumes, signal timings and trip generations using Synchro and Vissim for an 800m stretch of fifty rd between Hwy 8 and South Service Rd. Assisted team members with studies, plans, research, reports, presentations, and proposing alternatives related to the project as well as references to relevant technical manuals such as MTO Design Manual and National Manuals of Uniform Traffic Control Devices for signal warrants and design specification.

Granite Club Construction (2012)

Coordinated the construction of a three-level recreation building located at 2374 Bayview Ave in Toronto. Reviewed shop drawings and carried out different types of inspections including LEED Inspections. Submitted the document to the consultants and took care of the permits from the city. Distributed Request for information, change orders and Site instruction among the team.